Guide to the Pease Family Collection of Sketchbooks and Exercise Books
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Sketchbooks and drawings, Series I
  - Emma Gurney Pease
    - Sketchbook: Scotland, 1853; Pease, Emma Gurney, circa 1830-1895; 1 v. (14 leaves of drawings); 12 x 27 cm. Bound in quarter green morocco and green cloth. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains graphite drawings from a family trip to Scotland in 1853. The majority of pages in the sketchbook are blank. One sketch is labeled as having details added by "A. Lloyd," presumably a friend of Emma's. As is typical for Emma, the subject matter is that of scenes from nature or views of villages and architectural features from a distance. The sketches are mostly very complete and include a panoramic waterfront view done over two facing pages. Locations depicted include: Stirling, the Falls of Bruar, Loch Tummel, Tummel Bridge, Loch Goil (?), Fort Augustus, Iona, the Treshnish Isles (and the "Bac Mor," or "Dutchman's Cap" rock formation), Oban, Tay nuit (Muckcairn?), and Ellswater(?).
      Scotland -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Scotland; Sketchbooks
    - Drawings: Nice, France, 1874; Pease, Emma Gurney, circa 1830-1895; 8 leaves of drawings; most 25 x 32 cm. Unbound. (Box Oversize 1, Folder 1)
      Contains drawings in graphite and gouache, of scenes around Nice, France. The subject matter includes rural scenes and local residents, landscapes, mountain and waterfront views, and architectural features.
      Travel sketches -- France; Sketchbooks; Nice (France) -- Pictorial works
  - Francis Richard Pease
    - Sketchbook: scenery and domestic objects, 1854-1857; Pease, Francis Richard, 1844-1865; 1 v. (ca. 30 leaves of drawings); 21 x 28 cm. Bound in blue printed boards, from an unidentified stationer/publisher. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Contains graphite drawings of scenery and domestic objects. Francis Richard Pease began this sketchbook when he was roughly 10 years old. Drawings are dated from 1854 to 1857. The drawings of scenery depict houses and other buildings, including churches and ruins. Objects drawn include a press, a stool, a model tin pump, an easel, and a vase.
      Sketchbooks
  - Helen Blanche Pease
    - Flower drawings, 1882; Pease, Helen Blanche, 1865-1951; 1 v. (20 leaves of printed plates and 2 leaves of drawings); 25 x 19 cm. Bound in publisher's original green cloth, with title stamped in gilt. (Box 2, Folder 8a)
      Consists of two graphite drawings by Helen Blanche Pease within the following published work: Hulme, F. Edward. Flower Painting in Water Colours. London: Cassell & Co., [1881?]. The front endleaf is inscribed: Helen Blanche Pease, 1 Jany. 1882. Hulme authored several series of this title, circa 1880-1885. The present volume appears to be the first series. The title pages and other preliminaries have been neatly excised in this copy. It retains all 20 chromolithographed plates of common flowers. Helen appears to have taken minimal interest in the volume; she has copied in graphite but two specimens (the crocus and the Eschscholzia) on blank leaves facing the illustrated plates.
  - Jane Gurney Pease
    - School drawing book, circa 1840?; Pease, Jane Gurney, 1827-1894; 1 v. (22 leaves of drawings); 24 x 30 cm. Bound in half maroon roan and marbled boards. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Contains varied drawings in graphite and watercolor. They are generally skillful drawings, with graphite landscapes and watercolor botanical studies. Most of the landscapes depict rural and/or possibly local scenery, with one of them labeled "Darlington." Many of the drawings and paintings here mirror those in her sister Emma's sketchbook of the same period (Box 1, Folder 2).
      Botanical illustrations; Sketchbooks
    - Sketches: Yorkshire, 1849-1850; Pease, Jane Gurney, 1827-1894; 6 leaves of drawings; 26 x 21 cm. Unbound. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Contains six graphite sketches of scenes in North Yorkshire. The sketches are rough, and lack detail. Labeled drawings include: Skinningrove, Mulgrave Castle, Guisborough Abbey, and Easby Abbey.
      Yorkshire (England) -- Pictorial works; Sketchbooks
    - Sketchbook: Switzerland and Cornwall, 1851-1852; Pease, Jane Gurney, 1827-1894; 1 v. (23 leaves of drawings); 19 x 27 cm. Bound in half dark green roan and marbled boards, from Harrison Penney, stationer, Darlington. (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Contains graphite and watercolor drawings from a family trip to Switzerland in 1851 and a second trip to Cornwall in 1852. As is typical of Jane's work, the sketches are all landscapes of one kind or another, showing mountains, lakes, notable architectural features like Chillon Castle in Switzerland, and scenes from villages. In addition to the drawings made in Switzerland, the pieces from the trip to Cornwall consist of seascapes and landscapes. In particular, Jane includes a sketch of Cotham Lawn estate, which belonged to Margaret and Richard Fry. The Fry family was related to the Peases through marriage by this time. Other places depicted include: Lago di Como, Lago Maggiore, Montreux, Fribourg, Thun, Vevey, Heidelberg Castle, Giessbach Fall, Mainfort—Cornwall, Mount's Bay from Penzance, and Falmouth harbor.
      Cornwall (England: County) -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- England; Switzerland -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Switzerland; Sketchbooks
  - John Henry Pease
    - Sketchbook: seascapes and landscapes, circa 1850; Pease, John Henry, 1836-1854; 1 v. (12 leaves of drawings); 26 x 37 cm. Bound in green paper wrappers with gilt lettering on cover reading "Drawing Book. Geo. Rowney & Co., London." (Box Oversize 1, Folder 2)
      Contains graphite drawings and watercolors of waterfront views and rural architecture. The drawings vary in degree of completeness, but show a range of interest and fairly skillful handling. Two inserted drawing by Emma Gurney Pease depict Mulgrave Castle, in Yorkshire, and a scene from Marske by the Sea. Both are done in graphite and watercolor.
      Sketchbooks; Marines (Visual works)
  - Mary Cecilia Pease
    - Portfolio of juvenile drawings and paintings, circa 1906-1909; Pease, Mary Cecelia, 1892-1975; 1 portfolio (54 leaves of drawings, various sizes); the volume measures 51 x 40 cm. (Box Oversize 1, Folder 3-5)
      Contains 54 individual pieces of artwork and a "Scholastic Drawing Book" by Mary Cecelia Pease. The drawings and paintings are in graphite and/or watercolor and represent a wide array of subject matter, from botanicals to portraits, still lifes, landscapes, and others. Many of the watercolors have tiny holes in them, suggesting they may have been pinned up somewhere (Mary's schoolroom at home perhaps?) or perhaps simply from being pinned to a drawing board/easel. The artworks are generally quite complete, with many studies included in the portfolio. On a few pieces, comments and what appear to be "scores" are given by an unidentified individual with the initials "L.W."
      Children's art
  - Mary W. Pease
    - Hutton Hall album, 1865-1890; Pease, Mary W.; 1 v. (39 leaves of drawings as part of the album, plus 22 additional items inserted); 33 x 43 cm. (Box Oversize 2)
      Contains drawings and watercolors by Lady Mary W. Pease, many concerning the family's Hutton Hall estate. The watercolors are done in a confident, accomplished hand. She seems to have had a particular talent for observation, composition, color, and in the handling of her paints. The works represent a close knowledge of the family home, record the style of décor that the Peases used, document family outings close by and further away (especially to Scotland), and show two other Pease properties. It includes still lifes of domestic items like cooking pots and utensils, botanical studies, and designs for wallpaper patterns. This album demonstrates Lady Mary's interest in her home and the way in which the home itself was a sort of canvas on which she expressed herself, as a prosperous Victorian wife.
      Hutton Hall was designed for Joseph Whitwell Pease in 1868 by architect Alfred Waterhouse, who is perhaps best known for his work in designing the Natural History Museum in London. Waterhouse was raised in a Quaker family and received many commissions to design homes for prominent Quaker families in the North of England. Some of his very trademark elements are the terra cotta and cream colored brick construction, and the Gothic stylizing that can be seen in Hutton Hall. Hutton Hall had its own railroad station on a line that ran from Middlesborough to Guisborough, an extension of the original Stockton and Darlington Railway, established to carry more of the mineral freight from mines to ports in the area. Both of these towns were significantly developed by the Pease industrial enterprises.
      It is not clear whether Lady Mary assembled this album herself or whether it was put together by another family member. Someone labeled these pieces in the twentieth century, long after her death, and it's possible that the physical album dates from the Victorian era. So, in a way, the idea of the "Hutton Hall Album" as a cohesive unit may not have been Lady Mary's exactly, although the number of paintings that are in it and their subject matter certainly shows us that the years, places, experiences depicted in the album are all sort of unified by the Hall, and by the period of time that the Peases occupied this house.
      Dwellings -- Pictorial works; Interior decoration -- Great Britain; Hutton Hall (Guisborough, England); Waterhouse, Alfred, 1830-1905
    - Sketchbook: Scotland and Wales, 1870s; Pease, Mary W.; 1 v. (20 leaves of drawings); 13 x 26 cm. Bound in contemporary dark green quarter morocco and green cloth. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Contains graphite and watercolor sketches documenting travels in Scotland, primarily. The subjects of Lady Pease's work include waterfront views, scenes of rolling hills and vegetation, studies of local residents, and architectural features. Most of the sketches are completed in watercolor. Some pieces depict scenes from Falmouth, Wales, where the Peases had a home called Kerris Vean. Labeled scenes include: Loch Bulig, Mar Lodge, Cluny Lodge Braemar, Behind Lions Face Cluny, Lemorran Creek, Penlee Point & Newlyn, Hanging Stone Hulton Stream, and Ballater & Crathie.
      Wales -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Wales; Scotland -- Pictorial works; Sketchbooks; Travel sketches -- Scotland
    - Sketchbook: Switzerland, 1886; Pease, Mary W.; 1 v. (23 leaves of drawings); 11 x 18 cm. Bound in contemporary quarter dark green morocco and dark green cloth. (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Contains watercolors made by Lady Pease during a family trip to Switzerland in 1886. The paintings are mostly very complete and depict landscapes observed throughout the voyage, from the Dover cliffs to the mountains and lakes of Switzerland. Labeled scenes include: Dover, Zurich, Silvaplana, Engadin, Poschiavo, St. Moritz, Thusis, Simplon, Chillon Castle, Lake Geneva, and Interlaken.
      Travel sketches -- Switzerland; Sketchbooks; Switzerland -- Pictorial works
  - Sarah Charlotte Pease
    - Botanical watercolors, 1880-1881; Pease, Sarah Charlotte, 1858-1929; 1 v. (15 leaves of drawings); 26 x 18 cm. Coverless sketchbook. (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Contains works signed "S.C.P.", the initials of Sarah Charlotte Pease. The botanical studies are done in watercolor throughout. Flowers depicted include roses, coneflowers, bush honeysuckle, Capsicum, lilies, poppies, and Buddleia. Several of the pieces are labeled "Ben Welldene," which was the home of the Hodgkin family, into which Sarah eventually married. Benwell Dene was designed by Alfred Waterhouse for Dr. Thomas Hodgkin, who later donated the house to the Royal Victoria School for the Blind. Other pieces were painted in Scotland, Germany, and at the Pease family home, Hutton Hall.
  - Unidentified Artist
    - Sketchbook: Switzerland, Germany, Italy, and France, 1857-1880; 1 v. (22 leaves of drawings); 19 x 27 cm. Bound in quarter dark roan and green cloth, with brass clasp. (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Contains travel sketches made between 1857 and 1880, by an unidentified member of the Pease family. All of the drawings are in graphite. The style and subject matter resemble those of Jane and Emma Pease, but the skillful handling suggests that the artist was probably Lady Mary W. Pease. The sketches depict scenes from Switzerland, Germany, Italy, and France. Labeled scenes include: Hallstadt, Cadenabbia, Bouverie (Lake Geneva), Splügen, Isola Bella (Stresa), St. Moritz, La Bollène, and Lake Como.
      Sketchbooks; Travel sketches -- Europe
- Exercise books, Series II
  - Edward Lloyd Pease
    - Examination books, 1869-1872; Pease, Edward Lloyd, 1861-1934; 5 v. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Contains academic examination papers for Edward Lloyd Pease, the son of Henry Pease. Dating from 1869-1872, when Edward was between the ages of eight and eleven, the items evidence evaluation in composition, history, religion, and mathematics. All writing is done in pen and black ink, although an instructor (an Algernon C.P. Coote) has made comments in purple ink in the 1872 test booklet. The instructor notes particularly that Edward should not "write about things…not in the question." The examination papers indicate that they were likely administered at Pierremont, Henry Pease's estate in Darlington. An 1874 roster for Oliver's Mount School in Scarborough, which includes Edward, shows that after these examinations, he advanced to the boarding school.
      Examinations
    - Science exercise book, 1876; Pease, Edward Lloyd, 1861-1934; 1 v. (60 p.); 23 x 19 cm. Bound in quarter green cloth and marbled boards. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Contains notes on zoology, geology, arithmetic, and engineering, by Edward Lloyd Pease, who was about fifteen years old at the time of the lessons recorded in it. Some of Edward's essays include illustrations of mechanical objects. Writing is in graphite or pen and black ink. It is possible that this schoolbook was used while Edward was at Oliver's Mount School, where he is listed on an 1874 roster. However, no instructor comments appear. A rather fanciful and spirited inscription by Edward appears on front pastedown: "Elementary Science/ comprising a treatise on Astronomy/Natural Philosophy/ Geology &/ Mensuration Formulae/ An abridgment [sic] from ther [sic] larger works on these subjects, which have been carefuly [sic] consulted by Mr. Robinson, and drawn up in such a manner that it is likely to prove the greater boon to students interested in these subjects published by/ E.L. Pease. A.A.S.; B.A; A.R. A; B.C.L.B.M.: C.B.S; B.C. L; F.R.S: F.S. A: L.L. B: L.L.D. etc. etc. etc. etc./ 100,000,000,000th edition/ This work is dedicated (by the kind permission of his most gracious majesty) & the most noble King of the Cannibal Islands./ Opinions of the Press: This wonderful little work is marvelously adapted after…."
      Science -- Study and teaching; Exercise books
  - Emma Gurney Pease
    - Mathematics exercise book, 1839; Pease, Emma Gurney, circa 1830-1895; 1 v. (132 p.); 24 x 19 cm. Bound in quarter red roan and marbled boards. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Title page is inscribed "Emma Pease, Darlington, 1839" in an elaborate calligraphic hand. Exercises are written in pen and black ink throughout. It contains dozens of mathematical exercises, primarily in practical topics, such as "Addition of Money, Weights, and Measures," "Ale or Beer Measure," "Land Measure." The practical problems may have been meant to give a child a more concrete grasp of the application of mathematics, or perhaps they were meant to prepare a young female student for future management of a household.
      Exercise books; Mathematics -- Study and teaching
    - Mathematics exercise book, 1841; Pease, Emma Gurney, circa 1830-1895; 1 v. (128 p.); 24 x 19 cm. Bound in quarter roan and marbled boards. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Inscribed "Emma Gurney Pease Darlington, 3rd Mo. 8th 1841." It continues the practical or topical mathematical exercises of her 1839 schoolbook. All writing is in pen and black ink. Each problem is labeled in a child's calligraphic hand, showing that Emma took pride in the appearance of her schoolbook, and that these exercises afforded her further opportunity to practice her handwriting. Exercises in this schoolbook include financial transactions and topics, such as "Stocks," "Brokerage," and "Simple Interest," perhaps reflecting the visibility and importance of the Pease family's banking business at this time.
  - Henry Pease
    - Penmanship exercise book, 1816; Pease, Henry, 1807-1881; 1 v. (20 p.); 20 x 17 cm. In paper wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Contains handwriting exercises throughout, the themes of which reflect such values as hope and the precariousness of wealth. Henry Pease created this schoolbook at the age of eight or nine. He carefully signed several pages, "Henry Pease, Darlington." All material is written in pen and black ink. It is not known what school Henry attended, and there are no instructor comments in this particular exercise book. Most likely he attended a local nonconformist school.
      Exercise books (Penmanship); Exercise books
    - Mathematics exercise book, 1817; Pease, Henry, 1807-1881; 1 v. (ca. 50 p. of exercises); 21 x 18 cm. Bound in quarter calf and marbled boards. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Contains exercises in mathematics, in pen and black ink, done when Henry Pease was nine or ten years old. Multiplication and division exercises are accompanied by prose descriptions of the various sorts of mathematical methods. There is no indication of the name of Henry's school or instructor.
    - Penmanship exercise book, 1821; Pease, Henry, 1807-1881; 1 v. (16 leaves of exercises); 20 x 33 cm. Bound in quarter calf and marbled wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Contains penmanship exercises, in pen and black ink, by Henry Pease. Moral values, such as the fear of wickedness, the importance of modesty, and avoidance of foul language, are promoted via the exercises. There are no instructor comments and there is no indication of the name or location of Henry's school.
    - Composition book, 1821; Pease, Henry, 1807-1881; 1 v. (circa 50 p.); 16 x 20. In marbled paper wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Contains compositions, in pen and black ink, by Henry Pease. Includes some instructor comments in red ink. Henry's compositions range in theme from English and world history, to ethics, to favorite hobbies and sports. Particularly notable are an essay "On the Pleasures of the Approaching Vacation," a piece debating warfare, and another about winter sports, which for Henry included snowballing, "sliding" (sledding), and skating.
      Composition (Language arts) -- Study and teaching; Exercise books
    - Latin exercise book, 1823-1825; Pease, Henry, 1807-1881; 1 v. (40 p.); 18 x 24 cm. In buff paper wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      The pages of this exercise book have been thriftily used during two separate years. The recto sides of the pages are dated 1823 and 1824, and the verso sides have been used (with the book flipped upside down) in 1825. The 1823/1824 portion contains Latin exercises; the 1825 portion consists of penmanship exercise. All are written in pen and black ink; some comments from an instructor or an older pupil--a John Irvine (or Irving)—appear on a few of Henry's Latin exercises. Henry, in turn, notes where he has amended any errors. Moral values, as is typical of the Pease family schoolbooks, are promoted via the handwriting exercises throughout, with hard work and modesty being among the themes here.
      Latin -- Study and teaching; Exercise books
  - Multiple Authors
    - Juvenile Compositions, 1843-1846; Pease, Jane Gurney, 1827-1894; Pease, Rachel, 1831-1912; Pease, Emma Gurney, circa 1830-1895; Pease, Elizabeth Lucy, 1833-1881; 1 v. (76 p.); 20 x 24 cm. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      This schoolbook is the joint project of four Pease sisters: Emma, Jane, Rachel, and Elizabeth. It contains various essays on topics such as who the best king of England was, and about the different seasons. All writing is in pen and black ink; a couple graphite sketches accompany one or two essays. Within the schoolbook, there are some creative compositions, including poems and "A Letter supposed to be written by the page of an English nobleman during the crusades to his sister at home, Ascalon (?), 1192." A very unexpected 1845 essay on Hydropathy as a treatment (something that had only just debuted in England in about 1843), is written by Elizabeth Lucy. Rachel's essay on "Winter" includes some poignant descriptions of "dirty" and "poor" children begging from door to door and avalanche victims in Switzerland. A graphite sketch of a rooster accompanies a piece on "the domestic cock" by Rachel Pease. All of the essay signatures indicate that they were written at Southend, the Darlington estate of Joseph Pease and the sisters' childhood home. The girls were most likely educated here.
      Exercise books; Composition (Language arts) -- Study and teaching